Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Crafts-person

+1-651-485-2195⊠ tamara@tamouse.org https://tamouse.org y tamouse tamouse

Summary

Working at the intersection of Rails, GraphQL, and React, developing modern web applications with fast response times. Deeply experienced in software architecture, design, development and deployment tools and methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of web applications, user experience, team building, and processes.

Skills

General software engineering, web development, mentoring, consulting, facilitating, teach-

ing, business analysis

Libraries + Rails, React, Vue, ApolloClient, ApolloServer, GraphQL, Sinatra frameworks

Languages Ruby, JavaScript, Python 3, Shell, CSS3,

SCSS/SASS, HTML5, PHP, Perl

Servers Netlify, nginx

Software APIs, architecture, backend, coding, de-

bugging, frontend, full-stack, GraphQL, engineering

low-level design, macro- and microservices, REST, testing, tool chains

Databases PostgreSQL, Redis, TimeScaleDB

> Aws S3, ECS, EC2, DynamoDB, RDS, Elasticache, Lambda, IAM, Amazon MemoryDB

for Redis, CloudFront, Route 53, API Gateway, CodeBuild, CloudWatch, KMS, Secrets

Tools Emacs and Org-mode, RubyMine, Web-

storm, rake, Thor, make, Node.js, webpack, babel, npm/npx, Storybook, yeoman (yo),

Miro, Notion

Testing Minitest, RSpec, Jest, Testing Library

Methods Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything – testing, integration, deployment (CT/CI/CD); Functional Programming; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Program architecture and design; NLP (Neurolinguistic Programming) practitioner; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Time series analysis; User-/task-centered design

Experience

2022 Senior Rails Engineer, Wherefour, Remote.

One of three full-time engineers working mainly with Rails on the back end, adding new features.

- Importing orders from a 3rd party
- Automating testing of a major new feature
- Fixing some defects and small asks from customer success

Staff Software Engineer, Drip, LLC, Remote. 2020-2022

> Primarily focused on providing consumer and market analytics, insights, and guidance in the Drip app that enables Drip customers to become more capable email marketers. Acted as a project manager to plan, document, and track projects for the team. Software architecture and design for major features in the insights area, and providing mentoring, direction and guidance to other engineers in Drip.

> Worked in fully scripted continuous testing, integration, and deployment system, including wiring scripts for CircleCI, AWS CodeBuild, Cloudwatch logging, Docker containers, and Terraform.

- Developed an architecture for providing recommendations, insights, and proposed next actions to Drip users (i.e. email marketers)
- Developed a microservice to deliver time scale metrics in order to speed up customer analytics pages
- Designed an architecture to provide a Guidance System that would be able to take requirements and copy for guidance from any product team and others, and provide it to the front end where needed based on metrics and benchmarks
- Member of the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion team at Drip, and led the DEI Affinity Groups project to produce a guide for forming and running affinity groups (i.e. employee resource groups) within Drip
- Led a team to produce a mentoring and learning environment at Drip, including a guide for mentors and mentees, tools to find or offer mentoring, connecting mentees with mentors, and reporting results
- In the absence of any project management or leadership in the insights area, acted to perform discovery, planning, discussion, documentation, and create the Epics and Stories for each project, and monitored seeing it through to completion
- 2017-2020 API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Kickserv Product, Minneapolis, Minnesota/Remote.

Software engineering across the entire application stack from the back end in Ruby on Rails with a PostgreSQL database, implementing a GraphQL server controller with various queries, types, mutations, and resolvers to implement a GraphQL API, and create a React front end that consumes that GraphQL API with ApolloClient in order to replace the legacy JavaScript code from over a decade of various implementation styles and libraries, giving a modern, cohesive approach to front end web application development.

- worked in a scripted environment for continuous testing and integation, and scripts to build containers for deployment to AWS ECS, EC2, S3, RDB, as well as some other AWS services along the way.
- created AWS Lamdas with AWS API Gateway to crunch uploaded customer files, deduplicate them, and move them to CloudFront for rapid downloads.
- developed the Rails GraphQL backend for the product.
- architected and developed the JavaScript front end code in React to provide a good separation of
 concerns ensuring testability and writing tests where none existed prior; lowering maintenance costs,
 and ensuring easy replaceability to enable new features to be added with less overall effort and more
 predictability.
- o built Rails models, controllers, views, and React components for new Kickserv features.
- rebuilt all the tooling for building, testing, and delivering front end code with the Rails application, using modern build technology such as webpack (using webpacker), jest, and the JavaScript Testing Library
- 2001-2017 **Independent Contractor**, *Pontiki Software Crafts*, Mendota Heights, Minnesota/Remote. Contract software development of web applications, websites, and tools
 - created a Ruby on Rails template for new applications that provided Ansible instructions to create the home development and testing environments, as well as higher level environments of QA, Staging, and Production.
 - developed features for several clients' web apps, complex SQL expressions and internal stored functions, and include payment processing for websites for subscriptions and drop-shipped orders.
 - o Clients: Ackmann and Dickenson, Software for Good, Bluewaterbrand, Novu, Shopzilla
- 1980-2001 Various positions, Hewlett-Packard (San Jose, Palo Alto, CA), Control Data (Arden Hills, MN).

 Internal Process and Technology Consultant, Senior Software Engineer/Scientist, Software Engineer

 Manager of 10 engineers, Senior Software Quality Engineer
 - o 10 years as Internal Cunsultant helping software teams level up in productivity and quality
 - o 3 years Senior Software Engineer developing tools for network configuration and management
 - o 2 years Software Engineering Manager with 10 software engineers
 - 5 years Senior Software Quality Engineer running a networking interoperability test lab and quality engineering on a technical team producing TCP/IP

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA.

Additional Training

Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neurolinguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on React, Webpack, GraphQL, JAMstack, Angular, others